A Guide to the Frank Repass Brown Papers, 2004.3
Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
Frank Repass Brown Papers 1788-1975, undated.
Special Collections, Kegley Library
2004.3
3.5 linear feet..
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by the estate of Martha Brown DeBord in September 2004.
Biographical Information
Frank Repass Brown, son of Michael Dallas Brown and Emily Repass Brown, was born on 27 March 1887 in Rural Retreat, Virginia. He attended school in Rural Retreat and business college in Kansas. He returned to Virginia and graduated from Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Upon his graduation, he assumed management of the family farm in Rural Retreat and embarked upon a lifelong love and service in the field of agriculture. He was a charter member of the Rural Retreat Community Fair as well as a member of Future Farmers of America. He received an honorary degree from Future Farmers of America in recognition of his contributions to agriculture and farming in particular.
Brown shared his love of books and reading with many libraries in the region by making monetary and in-king donations of books and magazines. Rural Retreat High School Library, Marion College Library, and Southwest Virginia Mental Health Institute (then Southwestern State Hospital) in Marion, Virginia benefitted from his generosity.
He was a lifelong member of St. Paul Lutheran Church in Rural Retreat and wrote a history of the church, Historical Sketch of St. Paul's Lutheran Congregation, 1776-1941. He served on the board of trustees for Marion College, a junior college for women, from 1924 to 1964
Brown collected and compiled lists of cemeteries in Wythe County, especially in the western portion. He also collected local history and kept several scrapbooks. Brown also recorded local weather, keeping records noting daily temperature and rainfall for over forty years. He also researched local history and genealogy of many area families.
Brown married Virginia Umberger in 1925; the couple had no children. He died on 12 October 1973 and is buried in Black Lick Cemetery. His collection was bequeathed to his niece, Martha Brown DeBord.
Scope and Content
The Papers are arranged into twelve series: Series I, Books, Religious (1788, 1828, undated); Series II, Cemetery Records (1898-1973, undated); Series III, Diaries, Personal (1905-1973); Series IV, Diaries, Vital Statistics (1896-1975); Series V, Ephemera (1815-1973); Series VI, Ledgers, Personal (1873-1975); Series VII, Ledgers, Genealogy (undated); Series VIII, Scrapbooks, Genealogy (undated); Series IX, Scrapbooks, Miscellaneous (undated); Series X, Scrapbooks, Local History (1896, 1913, undated); Series XI, Memoirs (1887-1960, undated); and Series XII, Photographs (undated).
Contents List
- Series I. Books, Religious. 1788, 1828, undated. (Box 1)
  - Folder 1. Repass Family Bible. 1788., 16"length x 11 3/4" width x 4 2/8" height.
    Repass Family Bible; printed in Nurnberg, Germany by Johann Andrea Endterischen Company. Introduction by Johann Michael Dillherns with acknowledgements to the German Kaiser, the King of Poland and the Crown Prince of Saxony. Frank Repass Brown kept the Bible during his lifetime and willed it to his niece Martha Brown DeBord. In German; conserved in 1963.
  - Folder 2. Little Catechism of Martin Luther. 1828., 4" width x 6" length x 1/2 depth.
    German, printed in Lancaster, Pa., cloth bound with leather spine.
  - Folder 3. German Study Bible. Undated., 4 1/4" width x 6 1/2" height x 1 1/8" depth.
    German study Bible with frontispiece and p. 1-14 missing; leather bound with metal clasps.
- Series II. Cemetery Records. 1898-1973 (Box 2)
  Frank Repass Brown compiled a loose-leaf binder of notes and maps on various local cemeteries in Wythe and adjoining counties. The original records are housed in acid-free folders in the Frank Repass Brown Papers, Series II. The records consist of lists of veteran burials, burials in miscellaneous cemeteries, and the cemetery compilation by Brown in which he divided Wythe County into four quadrants, mapped cemeteries, and listed burials.
  Photocopies donated by Beverly Repass Hoch (who copied the records in 1997 with permission from Martha Brown DeBord) may be found in the vertical file collection, "Wythe County Cemeteries - Frank R. Brown Records." Photocopies include all cemetery records except letters and financial accounts for various cemetery associations.
  - Folder 1. Cemetery Records - Cemeteries - Bethany - Mountain View. Undated.
    This folder contains lists of burials in Bethany Methodist Church Cemetery (west of Ceres), Cullop Family Cemetery in Smyth County (listed with Luther Chapel Cemetery), Kimberlin Cemetery, Lutheran Chapel Cemetery (Washington County, Va.), Mt. Mitchell Cemetery, Mt. Pleasant Methodist Church Cemetery, Mountain View Cemetery (Rural Retreat), and the Jefferson Neff Family Cemetery in Lee County, Va. (listed with Luther Chapel Cemetery).
  - Folder 2. Cemetery Records - Cemeteries - St. John - Zion. Undated.
    This folder contains lists of burials in St. John's Lutheran Church Cemetery, St. Paul Lutheran Church Cemetery, Sharon Lutheran Church Cemetery (Ceres), Steffey Family Cemetery (Groseclose), Derting and Bennington Cemetery (listed with Steffey Family Cemetery), Repass (west of Bland Court House; listed with Steffey Family), Davis Family Cemetery (Groseclose; listed with Steffey Family Cemetery), Thiel Creek Presbyterian Church Cemetery (Cleveland, Tenn.), Mt. Mitchell Cemetery (listed with Thiel Creek Cemetery), Mt. Pleasant Cemetery (listed with Thiel Creek Cemetery), Pleasant Hill Cemetery (listed with Thiel Creek Cemetery), Fairview (listed with Thiel Creek Cemetery), Zion Cemetery (Crockett, Va.), and Zion Methodist Episcopal Church Cemetery (Marion).
  - Folder 3. Cemetery Records - Cemetery Compilation, part 1 (p.1-16). Undated
    This folder contains part one of the cemetery compilation arranged and organized by Brown. Using a Wythe County road map, he divided the county into four quadrants and plotted each cemetery on this map; a copy of this map is in each folder containing Cemetery Compilation records. Brown also developed an alphabetical index to the cemeteries, linking each entry on individual cemeteries to quadrant letters and numbers corresponding to the map. For example, the location of the Foglesong cemetery may be found on quadrant section A, cemetery number 1.
    Cemeteries included in this folder include (following Brown's compilation order): Foglesong, Neff, Doak, Newland, Fry, Earhart Ward, Pruner, Wauker, Buchanan (3), Phillippi, Steffey, Keesling, Vaught, Phillippi, Horn, Etter, Vaught, Engledove, Peery, King, Shelton, Richardson, Pennington, Orr, Cassell, Litz, Aekers, Snavely, Kettering, Newland, Hillenburg, Umberger, Kegley, Wohlford-Grubb, Corvin, Harkrader, Brown, Cassell, Umberger, Walters, Grubb, Henley, Gose, Percival, Fry, Gannaway, Mathews, Painter, Arney, Sanders-Whitman, Davis, Crockett, McGavock, Keesling, Toncray, Huddle, Simmerman, Gregory, Pierce, Hudson, Allison, and Walters.
  - Folder 4. Cemetery Records - Cemetery Compilation, part 2 (p. 17-30). Undated
    Cemeteries in this folder include (following Brown's compilation order): Oglesby, Cooley, Warder, Montgomery, Crockett, Patterson, Halsey, McGavock, Seyhert, Jones, Shaffer, Thorn, Crockett, Danner, Pearman, Pine Grove, Vaughan, Ogle, Stevans, Gannaway, Kirk, Shupe, Morgan-Trigg, Huddle, Red Bluff, Spence, Byrd-Neese, Wisely, Baker, Sayers, Williams, Buntz, Watts, Blair, Ward, Hudson, Raper, Jackson (2), Hinz, Baker, Fry, Booth, Pine Grove, Simmerman, Davis, Graham, Monks Corner, Derian and Mabe.
  - Folder 5. Cemetery Records - Cemetery Compilation, part 3 (p. 31-40, [41-42]). Undated.
    Cemeteries included in this folder include (following Brown's compilation order): Kent, Jackson, Walters, Painter, Huddle, Clark, Mundy, Trigg, Pierce-Umberger, Federal Troops, Jackson, Catron (2), Pope, Chadwell, Early, Earhart, Bell, Sayers-Bell, Ayers, Wright, Robinson, Porter, Jackson, Aker, Arnold, Earhart, Catron, Tompson, Suiter, Crockett, Poor Farm, Simmerman, Nye (Armbrister), Robinson, Ricky Porter, Blair, Hollandsworth, Davis, Groseclose, Six, Wetzell, and Federal Troops.
  - Folder 6. Cemetery Records - Cemetery Compilation, part 4 (n.p.) Undated.
    Cemeteries included in this folder include (following Brown's compilation order): Peery, Wauker, Buchanan, Phillippi, and Sanders. Also included is a handwritten article on cemeteries in the Black Lick section of Wythe County, note "Family Cemeteries in Wythe County to Look Up," and "Miscellaneous Cemetery Notes." This last article contains information on the burial of Federal Troops, White Top Cemetery, and West End Cemetery. Also included in this folder are notes on burials from notebooks of Mrs. Philip Spence that includes Counselman, Miller, Raper, Graham, Shaffer, Crockett (Newberry Farm), Elbert Simmerman Farm, and John Trigg. Also included is article "Our Cemeteries in the West End of Wythe County."
  - Folder 7. Cemetery Records - Black Lick Cemetery Association. 1934-1968.
    This folder includes regulations, financial reports, letters, and other records of the Black Lick Cemetery Association of which Frank Repass Brown was a member.
  - Folder 8. Cemetery Records - Black Lick Cemetery Association. 1969-1970.
    This folder includes financial reports, letters, and other records of the Black Lick Cemetery Association of which Frank Repass Brown was a member.
  - Folder 9. Cemetery Records - Black Lick Cemetery Association. 1971-1973.
    This folder includes financial records, letters, and other records of the Black Lick Cemetery Association of which Frank Repass Brown was a member.
  - Folder 10. Cemetery Records - Kimberlin Cemetery Association. 1963-1973.
    This folder includes regulations, financial reports, letters, and other records of the Kimberlin Cemetery Association of which Frank Repass Brown was a member.
  - Folder 11. Cemetery Records - St. Paul Cemetery Association. 1942-1968, undated.
    This folder contains correspondence regarding state funding for maintenance of graves of Confederate veterans in St. Paul's Lutheran Church Cemetery, a list of Virginia cemeteries receiving state support for Confederate grave maintenance, and records of the St. Paul Association. Also included are newspaper clippings (photocopies).
  - Folder 12. Cemetery Records - Confederate Pensioners, Captain Blessing's Company, and Joseph Brown Records. Undated.
    This folder contains "A List of Confederate Pensioners Who Have Drawn Pensions from Wythe County Since 1902," list of members in Captain Blessing's Company, and letter from Edward F. Witsell of the War Department to Mrs. N. Bruce Williams regarding Civil War records of Josiah Brown.
  - Folder 13. Cemetery Records - Confederate Veterans Burials. Undated.
    This folder contains a list of Confederate veterans who are buried in Asbury Cemetery, Fairview Cemetery, Lebanon Cemetery (on back of Fairview listing), Kimberlin Cemetery, King's Grove Cemetery, Marvin Cemetery, Rural Retreat (Mountain View), St. John's Lutheran Cemetery, St. Paul Lutheran Cemetery, and Zion Cemetery.
  - Folder 14. Cemetery Records - [Visit to Point Lookout Cemetery, Maryland]. 1950.
    This folder contains Brown's "A Visit to My Grandfather Repass' Last Resting Place, August 17, 1950," regarding his visit to the Point Lookout Prison cemetery in Maryland to see the burial site of his grandfather, Gordon Repass. Brown described the cemetery and included photographs in his typescript. Also included is a letter from the War Department to Sally Maupin regarding service record of Gordon Repass.
  - Folder 15. Cemetery Records - War Veterans. 1898-1945.
    This folder contains lists of veterans who served in the Spanish-American War, World War I, and World War II.
  - Folder 16. Cemetery Records - Miscellaneous. 1915-1953, undated.
    This folder includes miscellaneous records including a Wythe County Highway map (1950), letter regarding the Mt. View Cemetery Association (1951), map of Corinth Lutheran Church Cemetery, typescript of will of Emma Maria Doak (1951) and opinion regarding her legacy for maintenance of Marvin Cemetery (1953), and a poem entitled "Our Cemetery." Also included is a poem entitled "The Memorial," article "Birthplace of Memorial Day," article "God's Acre," article "monuments to Those Dead," and newspaper clippings including "List of Surviving Confederate Veterans" by Lindamood [incomplete] and members of Co. H, 63rd Virginia Infantry Regiment C.S.A. A newspaper clipping about Royal Oak Presbyterian Church Cemetery (Marion) and Rural Retreat High School are also in this folder.
- Series III. Diaries-Personal. 1905-1973. (Box 3)
  Frank Repass Brown recorded weather data and brief notes on daily life in these diaries.
  - Diaries, Personal 1. 1905-1916.
    This leather bound diary contains entries from 1 January 1905 to 31 December 1916. Most entries record weather and brief comments on daily life.
  - Diaries, Personal 2. 1917-1927.
    This leather bound diary contains entries from 1 January 1917 to 31 December 1916. Most entries record weather and brief comments on daily life.
  - Diaries, Personal 3. 1928-1939.
    This leather bound diary contains entries from 1 January 1928 to 31 December 1939. Most entries record weather and brief comments on daily life.
  - Diaries, Personal 4. 1940-1953.
    This leather bound diary contains entries from 1 January 1940 to 31 December 1953. Most entries record weather and brief comments on daily life.
  - Diaries, Personal 5. 1954-1964.
    This leather bound diary contains entries from 1 January 1954 to 31 December 1964. Most entries record weather and brief comments on daily life.
  - Diaries, Personal 6 1965-1971.
    This leather bound diary contains entries from 1 January 1965 to 31 December 1971. Most entries record weather and brief comments on daily life.
  - Diaries, Personal 7. 1954-1963
    This envelope contains loose typed pages dating from 1954 to 1963.
  - Diaries, Personal 8. 1900-1973
    This diary of loose-leaf pages consists of two parts. The first part contains weather data recorded by Frank Repass Brown for Wythe County as well as newspaper clippings relating to his record-keeping. This section has been photocopied and placed in Kegley Library Vertical File "Weather." The second part "Miscellaneous Dates" contains local and national events chronicled by Brown from 1900 to 1973.
- Series IV. Diaries, Vital Statistics. 1896-1975. (Box 3)
  Frank Repass Brown recorded vital statistics for people in the Rural Retreat vicinity of Wythe County including births, marriages, and deaths.
  - Diaries, Vital Statistics 1. 1896-1975.
    This leather bound diary contains records for births (1910-1957); marriages (1907-1973); and weather (1896-1975).
  - Diaries, Vital Statistics 2. early 1800s-mid 1900s.
    This leather bound diary with "Birthdays and Anniversaries" stamped on its cover contains births from the early 1800s to the mid 1900s arranged in calendar style.
  - Diaries, Vital Statistics 3. 1800s-early 1900s.
    This leather bound diary contains births from the 1800s to the early 1900s arranged alphabetically.
  - Diaries, Vital Statistics 4. 1800s-mid 1900s.
    This leather bound diary contains births from the 1800s to the mid 1900s arranged calendar style.
  - Diaries, Vital Statistics 5. 1887-1909.
    This envelope contains loose-leaf typed pages that record births from 1887 to 1909.
- Series V. Ephemera. 1815-1973. (Box 2)
  - Folder 1. Ephemera - Memorial Book for Ivan J. Brown. 1938, undated.
    This folder contains a memorial book for Ivan J. Brown, brother of Frank Repass Brown, whose funeral was held on 11 July 1938 at Marvin Church in Wythe County, Virginia. Also included are loose papers regarding the "Old Stone House" at the Rowan Museum in Salisbury, North Carolina, a "brown Family and Reunion" brochure, and various newspaper clippings on the Brown family.
  - Folder 2. Ephemera - Miscellaneous. 1815, 1956-1969, undated.
    This folder contains two programs (1957, 1969) for the Brown-Fisher reunion at Christiana Lutheran Church in Salisbury, North Carolina; Frank Repass Brown's "Notes on the Building of St. Paul Church;" historical sketch "St. Paul Lutheran Church;" sketch "Facts About the Rural Retreat Community;" a postcard of the home of Michael Brown in North Carolina; and a postcard of Grace Church in Rowan County, North Carolina. Also included are two photocopies of 1815 tax tickets for Henry Lambert and Michael Lambert and a newspaper clipping and photocopy about Frank Repass Brown being honored at the Virginia Association of Future Farmers meeting.
  - Folder 3. Ephemera - Correspondence. 1846, 1933, 1973.
    This folder contains three letters, a birthday card, and a fragment from a fraktur or baptismal certificate. A letter dated 7 March 1846 from Ephraim Brown and Elizabeth Brown of Hawkins County, Tennessee to Michael Brown of Wythe County discusses weather, health of neighbors, and their finances. In a 19 March 1933 letter, Orvil C. Sharitz of Newton, Kansas shares Sharitz family data with Frank Repass Brown. Another letter, from Margaret [unknown] of Pasadena, Texas to Frank Repass Brown, dated 8 August 1973, provides information on the Repass family.
- Series VI. Ledgers, Personal. 1873-1975. (Box 4)
  This series contains four ledgers kept by Frank Repass Brown for his personal accounts including income and expenses (1918-1972) and livestock accounts (1922-1958).
  - Ledger, Personal 1 - Marion College Alumnae. 1873-1925.
    This ledger contains a list of members of alumnae of Marion Junior College in Smyth County (1873-1925). The ledger lists in alphabetical and then chronological order the name of student (maiden name) with married name in parentheses (p. 2-252). A list in the back records members of the Wythe County Chapter, Marion College Alumnae (p. 197-200). The ledger is cloth bound with "Day Book" printed on the cover.
  - Ledger, Personal 2 - Income and Expenses. 1918-1972.
    This ledger contains a list of income (1918-1972; p. 2-69) and expenses (1918-1966; p. 100-338) for Frank Repass Brown. Each entry gives date, description, and to whom paid or from whom received, and amount. The ledger is leather bound with book mending tape on the boards.
  - Ledger, Personal 3 - Livestock Accounts. 1922-1958.
    Accounts relating to farm and livestock income and expenses are recorded in this ledger; pages have been placed in an acid-free folder. Accounts include livestock (1922-1958) and tax assessments on livestock (1931-1951). Also contained in this ledger is a contract and account records between Frank Repass Brown and G. W. Jones (1944-1959). Jones worked for Brown on his farm and received daily wages, one-third of the crop, house rental, and a cow.
  - Ledger, Personal 4 - Accounts. 1949-1975.
    Personal accounts of Frank Repass Brown (1949-1975) are recorded in this ledger whose pages have been placed in an acid-free folder.
- Series VIII. Scrapbooks, Genealogy. Undated. (Box 2)
  This series consists of three scrapbooks containing various genealogical information collected by Frank Repass Brown. Scrapbooks consist of pages removed from a leather ring binder; these pages have been re-housed in acid-free folders. Pages have been numbered in pencil and titles and descriptions noted on an index included in each folder. Some pages (those not excerpted from books, newspapers, and periodicals) with information on families and local history have been photocopied and placed in the Kegley Library vertical file collection.
  - Scrapbooks, Genealogy 1. Undated, 5 folders, 185 p.
    Topics include the following families: Dater/Tarter, Umberger, Etter, Yost, Phillippi, Shelton, Cline, Hounshell, and Catron. Also included is information on Crockett Depot, Civil War battles in Wythe County, Mount Airy, German settlers, and Rural Retreat. Folders are numbers 1 to 5.
  - Scrapbooks, Genealogy 2. Undated., 8 folders, 22 p., loose clippings.
    Topics include the following families: Brown, Cassell, Neff, Repass, huddle, Shannon, Wampler, Copenhaver, Sluss, Bedwell, Etter, Phillippi, Sharitz, Leedy, Stanger, Groseclose, Spangler, Miller, Dix, Litz, Catron, Staley, and Spence. Folders are numbered 6 to 13.
  - Scrapbooks, Genealogy 3. Undated., 6 folders, 194 p.
    Topics include the following families: Repass, Groseclose, Brown, Sluss, Huddle, Brown, Cassell, and Steffey. Folders are numbered 14 to 19.
- Series IX. Scrapbooks, Miscellaneous Undated. (Box 2)
  This series consists of three Scrapbooks containing various historical information collected by Frank Repass Brown. Pages have been removed from the leather ring binders and re-housed in acid-free folders. Pages have been numbered in pencil and titles and descriptions noted on an index included in each folder. Some pages (those not excerpted from books, newspapers, and periodicals) with information on churches have been photocopies and placed in the Kegley Library vertical file collection.
  - Scrapbooks, Miscellaneous 1. Undated., 8 folders, 158 p.
    Topics include: St. John's Lutheran Church, St. Paul Lutheran Church, Hawkins Chapel, Zion Lutheran Church, St. John's Episcopal Church, Corinth Lutheran Church, Salem Camp Ground, Grace Lutheran Church, Kimberlin Lutheran Church, Marvin Methodist Church, Black Lick Church, Mt. Zion Church, Macedonia Church, Rural Retreat Methodist Church, Christ Lutheran Church (Roanoke, Virginia), and Ebenezer Lutheran Church. Also included is information on Rev. Paul Henkel, Rev. George John Butler, Rev. John C. Repass, Rev. William P. Huddle, Rev. Elias Studebaker, Rev. William R. Brown, Rev. David Spangler Fox, Rev. Stephen Rhudy, Rev. William Carpenter, Rev. Henry Wetzel, Amos Copenhaver, Rev. Gideon Scherer, and baptismal certificates.
  - Scrapbooks, Miscellaneous 2. Undated., 8 folders; 199 p.
    Topics include: Zion Lutheran Church, St. Paul Lutheran Church, Kimberlin Lutheran Church, St. John's Lutheran Church, Sharon Presbyterian Church, and Sharon Lutheran Church.
  - Scrapbooks, Miscellaneous 3. Undated., 10 folders; 276 p., loose clippings.
    Topics include: lists of books Frank Repass Brown donated to local libraries including Rural Retreat High School and Southwest Virginia State Hospital, bibliographies, and other information on books.
- Series X. Scrapbooks, Local History 1896, 1913, 1943, undated. (Box 6, 7)
  - Scrapbooks, Local History 1. 1896, 1913, undated., 7 folders. (Box 6)
    This scrapbook with cloth spine and board covers contains newspaper clippings glued to scrapbook pages. Topics covered include Lead Mines, Revolutionary War, Wythe County history, and colonial era Southwest Virginia history. Several "The Southwest Corner," columns by Goodridge Wilson and "Wythe County History" columns (many excerpts from L. P. Summer's History of Southwest Virginia) are included. An index is housed with the scrapbook.
    Several loose newspapers clippings, booklets and ephemera are housed in separate folders that are described below. Photocopies of these loose clippings have been placed in the appropriate Kegley Library vertical file.
    - Folder 1. Scrapbooks, Local History - Loose Clippings - Churches. Undated.
      This folder contains seven loose newspapers clippings about St. Mary's Catholic Church, Fleming Methodist Church, Zion Lutheran Church, and St. John's Lutheran Church. Original clippings are housed in an acid-free envelope; photocopies of these clippings on acid-free paper are also in this folder.
    - Folder 2. Scrapbooks, Local History 1 - Loose Clippings - Freemasons. Undated.